[Music]
welcome back to my channel happy office
today we're gonna be taking a look at
how to crochet a flat circle now I've
currently I've currently I have actually
moved house in the last couple of weeks
and they're great timing and everything
and I've been obsessed with making lots
of lovely new coasters to go around the
house in this gorgeous mustard color and
the yarn that I'm currently in love with
if you follow me over on Instagram is
this Sid our number one chunky and oh it
feels just it's butchery is the only
word I can describe so i've crocheted
this flat circle using double crochet in
u.s. terms and the reason for that is it
builds up so quickly we've only got five
rounds I think I made about four or five
last night while my partner was watching
a movie I'm Sur chilling out on Easter
Sunday so really really nice sort of
perfect lounge activity providing your
cats obviously don't eat your yarn like
mine do so let's get started so for this
I'm using a five millimeter crochet hook
and you're going to start if I can't
afford my yarn here we go I'm going to
start with a magic circle and if you're
unfamiliar with how to crochet the magic
circle I pop a link above however the
way I do it is I wrap my yarn around my
two fingers like that
I take it over and cross it over I pick
my hook off and I pick up this one
spinning it round I then do a little
turn so that it's made a little cross
over there and then I pick back up the
yarn like so it is quite tricky for
beginners so I would recommend
definitely practicing it or watching the
other video and little bit more detail
so we're going to chain two and the
thing about my crochet circles is you
don't count the chain two as a stitch
now traditionally you would count your
chain two
your chain three as a stitch but I tend
to find that if you do though let me
just go out the back if you do that what
you get we take a look at this you will
see where your your seam has been now I
can see here very easily that my seams
there what you will get is you will get
some gapping or gaping not very nice
word like this so by keeping those chain
twos as extras and they don't really
affect the circle at all and make it
bulge what it does is it make sure it's
really nice and thick and full around
the join but it's completely up to you
if you want to ignore you know if you
want to ignore this and you want to
count this as a stitch please by all
means go ahead so once I've done my slip
knot or make my Magic Circle and do an
extra two chains and then we're going to
create 10 double crochets into the
circle so yarn over insert into the
little loop and Allie said hoop then
yarn over pull through two yarn over and
pull through two so exactly the same
again you're going to yarn over yarn
over pull through yarn over pull through
two yarn over pull through two just
realized that it's a little bit dark
[Music]
very case in daylight but when the sun's
bright filming it can be awfully
annoying anyway sorry about that let's
carry on so we've got our two double
crochets here and our chain of two so
we're going to do eight more so yarn
over insert into the hook yarn over pull
through two yarn over pull through two
and you're going to carry on all the way
until you've got ten so I'll do my ten
along with you so that we can do attend
together and I hopefully not have any
interruptions by me opening my blinds
for my cat scratching at the door I did
envisioned I'd be one of those extremely
polished in crochet youtubers with my
studio set up and everything going right
but I've learned that to know what real
life is real life and something will
always get in the way cat will always
eat my yarn or my partner will decide is
gonna put the washing machine on so I
don't know all the people have struggled
or please do share them with me what are
your biggest crochet interruptions even
if you just said crochet know you're
counting or the counting interruption I
mean how many bags and tote bags and
t-shirts have that on so here we go one
two three four five six seven eight nine
one more perfect
so once you've crocheted your 10 double
crochet give yourself a little bit of
room I mean you're going to locate your
tail and the best fit in the world and I
always feel this should be accompanied
by this noise as it closes talk that
nice and tight pop it round the back pop
your hook back in and then you're going
to join with a slip stitch now i doo doo
doo joined rounds and the reason we do
joined rather than continuous is because
it's such a tall stitch you're going to
want to join the rounds so what we're
going to do for me you see I've got my
one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten so I'm not going into this bit
yeah I'm actually going into my first
stitch so it looks nice I need so insert
for the slip stitch into that yarn over
and pull through and then pull straight
through the one that is on your hook and
there you have and then you can pull
this a bit tighter to close your circle
so I'm not going to change - and I
chained - traditionally you might chain
three for a turning chain four double
crochet I think because this yarn is a
little bit thicker on my my hook is a
little bit thicker the chain three is
too high but what's also worth noting is
I'm not trying to replicate a double
crochet I'm simply trying to get enough
height to do multiple crochets around so
then I'm going to place a double crochet
straight into the same stitch utter dead
there we go and then we're going to
place two double crochet in every one
all the way around so if you carry on
placing two double crochet when you get
round to the other end so and I'll just
do a few for those unfamiliar with the
double crochet so remember it's yarning
over inserting into a stitch yarning
over pulling back through your awning
over pulling through - yawning over
pulling through - so yarn over insert
into the same place cause of placing two
yarning over and pulling back through
your awning over pulling through two
yarn over pulling through two pulling
some more yarn up if only there was you
could teach animals to pull your yarn so
that you've got never-ending supply just
like yarn wouldn't that be great so two
double crochets in every stitch all the
way around or if you haven't tried this
sadar number one chongqing I would
definitely recommend heading here from
banks on I use wool warehouse for most
of my yarn and that the service is
fantastic and the collection is just
just really really good in terms of
pricing I think
they're relatively competitive I mean if
you do have a local yarn store I do
always say you know please do support
they'll call is really really important
and you also find that there's a really
nice crochet community or fiber arts
knitting community at your local stores
but it's certainly when you've got if
you like me and a trip into town feels
you with dread I tend to buy a lot of
stuff online
okay so we're nearly background at the
end I've got a couple more to go and
then I'll show you how I do the end so a
little bit of a split stitch I tend to
find just one do it
start again perfect so as a quick recap
can you see we've got two four six eight
ten twelve fourteen sixteen eighteen and
then the two here is only actually a one
for me
and the reason I like to keep it as a
war if I'd kept it as a two can you see
we've got quite a big gap to bridge
there which would work but for me I tend
to find that it always ends up leaving
me a gap so I place another one in this
stitch here which is the stitch that my
chain two is coming out of so I place
another one which takes up to 20 and
then I hop over here and I place my
single crochet in and voila there we go
can you see very nice so if you're
familiar with a circle increase this bit
should be a doddle for you however if
you're not what I'm going to do is I'm
going to talk through and I'll put some
prompts up on the screen so with the
circle you always do your number of
stitches in the center and then you
always double them here so we're going
to imagine
that this is I did 10 so we're getting
imagine it's a pie stick with me guys a
pie with ten slight imaginary slices and
every slice on every round has one more
stitch so if we take one slice in this
one it has one in this one it had two in
the next one it would have three and in
the next one it would have four so on
this next round every section of two
we've got
we need to make three so we do that by
do my chain of two by doing one double
crochet and then two in the next one
and I don't really know where the pie
came from but it just was a way to
visualize to people how those increases
happened
so we've taken two stitches and we've
turned them into three so we do one in
the next one and then we're going to do
two in the next one
yeah one in the next one
two in the next one I'm going to stop
saying one in the next one and two in
the next one cuz I'm pretty sure we've
got that but if we crochet along
together and have some random chitchat
so it's currently Easter Monday here a
little bit dog where I am I live in a
little village not far from a city
called Lincoln not a lot to do what's
going to go on a bike ride
I don't know about you guys
what's the barbecuing yesterday I could
certainly smell that and lots of jobs
already been done so today is the
perfect day for filming so one than to
the moment to the moment and then later
on I think I'm going to do my favorite
activity which is a good old Instagram
scroll of some of my favorite crochets
and I've actually got a video last week
I pop a link below with my my current
favorite five inst crochet Instagram
accounts and I mean cutting it down to
five was certainly tricky so please do
check it out and I'd love to hear your
your favorite Instagram accounts I used
to find that Pinterest was probably the
best area to go and certainly for
patterns and things Pinterest is still
one of the best places and obviously
revelry
however Instagram just for inspiration
and oh the photography there Oh amazing
amazing stuff some really talented
people on there so what I like to do
here is I'm just double checking cuz I'm
chit-chatting away that I am doing my
warm on my too and my warm on my too
because we're using the double crochet I
don't tend to find that you need to use
stitch markers however if you are more
comfortable using a stitch marker please
do you can quite easily kind of see
the end of the round is if you're using
continuous rounds then definitely do a
stitch marker I can't tell you the
amount of times I've thought oh I don't
need a stitch marker I'm an experienced
crochet big mistake no matter how many
years you've been crocheting do not
think you don't need stitch markers
you're gonna spend a lot of time pulling
your work down in frustration so I've
just on my last two and I'm very close
so I know that where I'm at now is it's
certainly very close so what we're gonna
do is we're going to just do a little
count up here so we're going to count 1
2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17
18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28 29 30
and we need 30 and 30 is the perfect
number so what I'm going to do is I'm
not going to be placing one here because
I only need 30 and I'm pretty confident
that that's gonna work quite nicely for
my 30 perfect so we've gone 10 20 30 and
the reason it's going up in ten is
because we've got 10 in the center so
whatever number it is in the center it's
always gonna go up by that number
so next imagine those pieces of pie one
stitch to stitch three stitch you've got
it we're going to put four stitches in
each section of three and it's really
really simple what you're going to do is
you're going to do one double crochet
and another single double crochet single
double crochet cracky if anyone was
listening that didn't know crochet they
would wonder what we're talking about so
single single and then an increase so
two singles and then an increase so
there we've taken our three and we've
made it all four and then our next one
more simple
three singles and an increase and you
can keep going as many as you want so
let's get on to this round and this can
actually be the final round I mean I
made my I'm aid this one a little bit
larger because I just wanted a little
bit more space around it just worked
nicely for mugs and things but it also
works nicely for kind of pots and plant
pots etc so let's go so a double a
double or split stage no a double a
double and then an increase and then we
have increase perfect watch is going off
at an almond notifications off bar/bat
sing go on so a double double and an
increase
she says she then skips over that's why
I was like to have a little check and
just go yeah I've got to there I've got
to there there's me telling you all to
you know hop down and do this while
you're watching the television and then
wondering why it's turn into you know a
little cone rather than a coaster so -
in this one if there's any other
patterns that you'd like to say I'm kind
of really enjoying these sort of small
shapes at the moment circle squares
hearts I'm certainly thinking I'm gonna
do a few moths anything that you you'd
really like to see I'd definitely be up
for doing that please pop a comment down
below and if you do like this video
please do give it a thumbs up it's one
of those really odd ones you tend to
watch videos you tend to subscribe to
people whose videos you like but I don't
know about you but I don't actually very
often give a video a thumbs up and yet
when you start filming your own videos
you realize just how much it really does
mean for people to give it a thumbs up I
think you're probably likely to get your
video show more maybe reach more people
so if you do like my crochet and my
random Easter Monday rumblings about how
lovely the weather is and whether my
cats ago now attack my yarn please give
it a thumbs up I posted on a Friday
every week there's always a new crochet
video I've recently been exploring some
new stitches because I do love textured
crochet works so if you are interested
in new crochet stitches learning
something different you know breaking
away from singles and doubles and color
I'm really keen to introduce neutrals
and plain colors but add interest and
variety through stitches and textures
and that's kind of the crochet journey
that I'm going on at the moment so if
you're kind of in the same place
yeah definitely
give me a year Chiqui subscribe and I'll
be back again on Friday with some new
bits ok so we've got to the end we've
done that we're gonna hop across here
and we're gonna can you see how that has
made a little bit of a gap now that
doesn't please me at all so I am going
to the first thing is to check and think
have I not done enough stitches but I
know I have done enough stitches but it
just so happens that the way it's fallen
so I am going to break all the rules I'm
going to put one more in there why not
who cares but one more in it's the last
round
if you are putting more more in just be
careful on the next round that you're
gonna have to just put one more in but
look at that look at that let's call
this no rules crochet so I'm going to
finish off so the way I like to do this
myself or if you haven't got these
darning needles they are an amazing set
of darning needles there's actually a
link below in the description to them on
Amazon where I pretty much buy
everything but the pack it's just such a
handy little pot I miss it we don't end
up down the side of the sofa like a lot
of needles do so what you're going to do
is you're going to snip off give
yourself a good 6 inches she says as she
cooks 18 inches pull that through and
then you're going to first time I mean
yeah
look have you seen the size of the hole
in this needle fabulous so this is the
bit that can be a little bit tricky what
I like to do is I like to pull it back
to the right as if we're finishing the
stitch and then I just like to take it
around and pop hit the needle focus
through the two there like this just
very gently making sure that I'm not
tugging it and making it quite clearly
that's the top of an or in
like that and then turn it over and then
to just make sure it doesn't get pulled
any more I just don't know why I'm
whispering it's almost like the cab not
careful you have to be the softy
okay so we'll turn it over so the aim
here is to take this yarn and weave it
all the way down to the middle because
this is quite chunky it's quite
forgiving it won't really matter where I
kind of poke it it's probably best not
to try and split your stitches if you
can help it and so I'm just gonna weave
that down there careful not to pull and
pull that bit in that should be okay
if you're using these as coasters like I
am you're probably going to find that oh
and look straight back into the little
handy holster whoa my needle holster
yeah you're probably going to find that
they're going to want to go in the wash
coffee stains and red wine stains and
various things so weaving this down and
then popping yourself a nice couple of
knots in the center is definitely going
to help them escape washing machine doom
and I like to put three in because it
doesn't really matter if there's a bit
of bulky knot on the back because you're
never going to see it so then a snip and
a snip some people like to secure that
using with a little bit of glue I tend
to find that's alright and there you
have those unsightly bits of yarn and
then you have your crochet coaster so
thank you ever so much
feel free to add another round if you'd
like one as big as this I mean it'd be
amazing you should do a series of them
series of different sizes in a
centerpiece really pretty some color
changing I am going to be doing a video
on color changing soon if you're
interested so it will be
of Lita maybe add like an axe and edging
on it and there's all sorts of amazing
ones I've seen them where they look like
slices of fruit or cat's heads and
things so I mean you really can't just
go coaster crazy am sure there's an
Instagram account called that so thank
you so much for watching I hope you've
managed to make yourself a successful
little circle and you've enjoyed my
random crochet ramblings I'll be back
next Friday make sure you subscribe hit
that notification bell happy hooking as
always I'll see you soon guys bye